Summer of the 24th year of Yuankang
六年の夏
Prince of Jin captured Dongming
晋王は東明城を攻め落とした
Defeated the imperial army
官軍を大敗させる
News reached the capital
知らせが皇城に届いた
Officials were shocked
百官は驚いた
The court was shaken
朝廷が動揺する
The people are most important
民を貴ぶ
The state comes second
社稷は次に位置する
The ruler is least
君は軽い
Princess Consort
王妃
When I went out just now
さっき出かけたとき
I heard news
ニュースを聞く
His Highness has taken Dongming
王爺はすでに東明城を制圧しました
Mother
娘
Is Father coming back to get us?
お父さんが迎えに来てくれることになった
Yes
そうだね
Father is coming back
パパが帰ってくるんだ
What did Mother teach you before?
娘が以前あなたに何を教えたか
Listen to Father
お父さんの言うことを聞かなければならない
Father has great things to do
パパは大きなことを成し遂げるつもりです
Don't cause Father trouble
お父さんに迷惑をかけない
Sheng'er is good
盛ちゃんお利口さん
Today I come on behalf of His Majesty
私は今日陛下を代表して参りました
This
この封筒
Is an edict personally written by His Majesty
これは陛下自らが起草された勅命です
The edict speaks of two things
詔書には二つのことが書かれていた
First
その一
The treacherous chancellor Chen Dao has corrupted the court
奸相である陳が朝廷を混乱させる
His Majesty now understands the truth
陛下は今すでに内情を明らかに理解されている
Wishes to remove the treacherous chancellor
奸臣を罷免しようとする
And execute the corrupt officials
奸臣を誅する
Second
その二
His Majesty deeply understands
陛下はよくご存じです
All of you present today
本日ご出席の皆様
Are all heroes of the northern expedition
皆が北伐の功臣です
Not rebels
逆賊ではなく
His Majesty will not only not punish
陛下は罰せられるどころか
But will heavily reward you all
皆さんにさらに多額の報酬を与えます
Hopes you will do your utmost
どうか心を尽くして努力してください
To recover the homeland soon
一日も早く故国に戻る
The court will reward us
朝廷は私たちに賞を与えようとしている
Wonderful
すごいです
His Majesty also has words for me to bring to Your Highness
陛下はまだお言葉をお伝えするよう私に頼まれました殿下
A family has come to this state
家族みんながこんな騒ぎになってしまった
What kind of situation is this?
体裁を整える
Tell the second son
次男と呼ぶ
To withdraw to the north
北へ退去する
Send his family
彼の家族を連れて行く
All to him
全部送って行く
This life
この日々
Can't be lived together
通れない
Then live apart
別れたことがある
After crossing the river
川を渡った後
He may raise
彼は建てられる
The imperial banner
天子の旗
North of Tianhe
天の川の北
All will be under his rule
すべて彼が管理する
Your Highness
殿下でんか
Accept the edict
お受けください